Today's דף ט', daf tet, we are still a little bit ahead.
Thank you Michael for yesterday. We pick up with about
where are we, about five lines from the bottom, מימרא דרבי יוחנן
הכי. meimre d'Rabbi Yochanan hachi. So the issue here is that the
משנה, Mishnah, we've been dealing with the different קרבנות החג. Korbanot of
the Chag. We dealt with which types of things have to come
from חולין, chullin, from non-sanctified or non-pre-obligated funds, which type of things
like the שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha could even come from pre-obligated funds.
We had the previous משנה Mishnah two back on ח' עמוד ב'
chet amud bet that dealt with people who have different means and
different needs and how to sort of distribute their money in terms
of the קרבנות. Korbanot. And this משנה Mishnah before it got to
an interesting דרשה drasha of מעוות לא יוכל לתקון meuvat lo yuchal
litkon discussed the whole issue about the idea of תשלומין, Tashlumin, that
the rest of the days one can make up if one did
not bring the קרבן חגיגה. Korban Chagiga. It does not address that
issue in terms of the עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah, although presumably it
is the same idea that there's a מצווה mitzvah primarily on the
first day, but one can make it up on later days. We
assume that discussion. And now we have left off with with this
debate spelled out between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי אושעיא, Rabbi
Oshaya, which is whether you say that the real obligation is the
first day and that any other day that one would bring it's
only making up because of the first day obligation. That's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says: תשלומין לראשון. Tashlumin lerishon.
And רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says: תשלומין זה לזה, Tashlumin zeh lazeh,
which it sounds a little imprecisely formulated, like every day is a
makeup for the previous day. It's more it seems more the accurate
way of describing it, although there's some discussion in תוספות, Tosfos, that
רבי אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya's way of phrasing it is more like any
day you can fulfill your obligation. Maybe there's a preference for the
first day, but any day you can fulfill your obligation. And then
the גמרא Gemara says the difference would be somebody that was not
obligated on the first day. It gives the example of the חיגר.
chiger. Now by the way, it is interesting to note and one
should just point out parenthetically that the חיגר, chiger, the lame person,
is the maybe not so parenthetically, the person who we excluded in
the first משנה Mishnah from which obligation? Does anybody remember?
Being עולת ראיה, Olat Re'iyah, right? So being פטור patur from ראיה,
Re'iyah, יראה כל זכורך yera'eh kol zechurcha and about being עולה לרגל,
oleh laregel, etc. This is a מצווה mitzvah of this משנה's Mishnah's
talking about חגיגה, Chagiga, מי שלא חג, mi shelo chag, right? So
it's quite interesting that they're assuming the exact same exclusions would apply,
right? For וחגותם אותו חג לה' שבעת ימים, vechagosem oso chag lashem
shivas yamim, etc., all those various verses do not explicitly connect to
the עלייה לרגל, aliyah laregel, the appearing in the מקדש Mikdash and
so on. So it's first worth noting the assumption here that this
is in the exact same category. The other point, as I said,
the issue about how you look at the other days as makeups
for the first day or as sort of an obligation on any
day. Presumably, I mean a very early תוספות Tosfos in the מסכתא
Masechta assumed that this debate here by the חגיגה Chagiga was the
same debate by the עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah. But again, that is
not spelled out in the גמרא, Gemara, but just in passing the
גמרא Gemara easily assumes that the חיגר chiger is exempt from the
חגיגה, Chagiga, which as we know until now is only an issue
by the עולת ראיה. Olat Re'iyah. So there's clearly an assumption that
these two are looked at in the same way. And that was
pretty implicit or somewhat sort of could be seen as somewhat implicit
in the previous משנה Mishnah that talked about how do you distribute
your money between the שלמי חגיגה Shalmei Chagiga and the עולת ראיה.
Olat Re'iyah. Like you spend a lot of money on one, a
lot of money on the other. How much money do you have?
How many what are your various needs? So they're definitely the way
in which these two are being looked at in a you know
in sort of in the same category. That's the first thing that
should be noted. Easier example, by the way, of somebody who is
exempt the first day, and it's funny that the גמרא Gemara doesn't
give it because this actually does happen in different contexts, if somebody
becomes בר מצווה bar mitzvah in the middle, right? What if what
if?
I mean a convert.
Converts, or as he said reverse- I'd like to figure out how
could you reverse. But anyway, that would be an example.
You know, you get this interesting question about ספירת העומר Sefiras Ha'omer
because that actually happens like one out of every you know one
out of every seven times. ספירת העומר Sefiras Ha'omer runs over 50
days, about one-seventh of the year. So about one-seventh of the boys
that become בר מצווה bar mitzvah become בר מצווה bar mitzvah during
the middle of ספירת העומר. Sefiras Ha'omer. Are they obligated if they
weren't if they weren't doing it as an obligation from the beginning?
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara though gives the example of the חיגר.
chiger. And the גמרא Gemara wants to know the person who is
lame, if he becomes better in the middle, is he obligated or
not? So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's all makeup for
day one, since he was exempt on day one he remains exempt.
And according to רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, that everyone is an independent
obligation, or one could say again that on any day one could
fulfill his obligation, then this person would be obligated even if he
was not obligated on day one. And with that the גמרא Gemara
picks up now five lines from the bottom. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן
הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Would רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really
say this, that somebody who was exempt on day one could not
fulfill his obligation the other days? He's considered completely out of the
category. ואמר רב חזקיה, Ve'amar Rav Chizkiya, חזקיה Chizkiya says, נטמא ביום
מביא. nitma beyom meivi. why and אינו מביא. eino meivi. Now this
is not really directly relevant and it's really an argument by analogy,
but let's take a look. It's not necessarily so persuasive, but let's
see what the גמרא Gemara is doing. So somebody here is a,
is a, what do you call it, is a מצורע. metzora. And
this מצורע metzora is in the process of becoming טהור. tahor. OK?
So and what happens? The story is is that he has to
wait seven days, right, and then begins his process. Hold on, let
me just check רש"י Rashi on one thing.
I'm sorry, no. He's a נזיר, nazir,
but one minute.
Oh, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. I'm jumping ahead to the next space.
OK, I'm sorry. I'm jumping ahead to the next space. OK, so
we'll start here. So the person is a נזיר. nazir. A נזיר
nazir brings a, you know, who who became טמא, tamei, goes through
a seven-day טהרה tahara process, right? He becomes טמא למת, tamei lemet,
goes through a seven-day טהרה tahara process, and then on day eight
brings a קרבן korban for his טומאה tumah and starts his נזירות
nezirut again. So the question happens, what happens if in the middle
of the seven-day process, let's take for instance an easy case, on
day three, after he's in the process of becoming טהור tahor after
having encountered a dead body, he touches another dead body? So clearly
he's not going to bring a second קרבן. korban. It's all a
continuation. He hasn't gotten out of his טומאה. tumah. So he waits
another seven days, and when he eventually gets out of the טומאה,
tumah, he'll bring one קרבן. korban. He had a long period of
טומאה, tumah, not seven days, ten days, because he touched a dead
body in the middle. Let's say however, now let's take another case
that's easy. In the middle of day eight, right, he finished his
seven days, he was ready to bring his קרבן korban on day
eight, and he touched another dead body. In that type of a
case, he'll have to bring two קרבנות, korbanot, right? Because one period
of טומאה tumah ended, he was obligated in his קרבן, korban, he
didn't get around to bringing it yet, he became טמא tamei again,
starts another period of becoming טהור, tahor, and then he and then
at the end of that seven days on day eight, he's obligated
in a second קרבן. korban. OK? So that's an easy case. The
interesting case is, what happens if he touches this dead body on
the night after the seventh, before the morning of the eighth? At
that time, after seven full days have passed and he's gone through
the sprinkling of the ashes and the whole thing, he is totally
טהור, tahor, but he is not yet able to bring the קרבן
korban until the daybreak, right? Because daybreak is you only bring קרבנות
korbanot in the day. Is he considered to have been out of
his period of טומאה, tumah, obligated in a קרבן, korban, although he
can't bring it yet, and therefore when he becomes טמא tamei again,
becomes becomes obligated again in a second קרבן? korban? Or is it
considered because he never had the opportunity or he wasn't even necessarily
maybe even considered fully obligated because he couldn't have yet brought it,
it's all a continuation of the same process? That's the debate of
חזקיה Chizkiya and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So let's take a look.
והאמר חזקיה, Veha'amar Chizkiya,
so חזקיה Chizkiya says, נטמא ביום מביא, בלילה אינו מביא.
Nitma bayom meivi, balaila eino meivi. No, even in the day.
No, because then he's already obligated in the second קרבן. korban. No,
the day of, the day of eight, as once it's daybreak he
becomes obligated and has the opportunity to bring a קרבן, korban, and
everybody agrees at that stage if he becomes טמא tamei again, it's
a second קרבן. korban.
אלא
לרבי שמעון.
Ela leRabbi Shimon. Ah, I don't know. OK. והאמר חזקיה, Veha'amar Chizkiya,
so חזקיה Chizkiya says, נטמא ביום מביא, בלילה אינו מביא. Nitma bayom
meivi, balaila eino meivi. If he became טמא tamei on day eight,
then he'll bring a second קרבן. korban. On the night before, he
would not bring a second קרבן korban and it would all be
a continuation of the טומאה. tumah. רבי יוחנן אמר אף בלילה נמי
מביא. Rabbi Yochanan amar af balaila nami meivi. And even at night
he'll also bring, it's already considered obligated. Now what the heck this
has to do with whether the first, you know, the obligation of
the חגיגה Chagiga is on is a makeup for day one or
each one is an independent obligation, I have no idea. But the
גמרא Gemara seems to be arguing this the following. Since רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan considers the person at night, although he's not able to
bring the קרבן korban at night, already in the category of the
קרבן korban because he will be able to bring it in the
day, the גמרא Gemara seems to be arguing that therefore somebody who's
let's say lame on day one is not fully excluded from the
category of the חגיגה. Chagiga. Maybe he'll become better in the you
know during the rest of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So even if
for technical reasons you cannot do the thing, you're not considered fully
excluded. So the גמרא Gemara might is seems to be saying, it
might be conceptually we're not questioning his position that things are a
makeup of day one, but we're questioning his assumption that if somebody
is lame on day one, they're completely not obligated. We see from
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that even if you can't bring something and
you're not able to, that doesn't completely put you outside of the
category.
A twisted ankle is like nighttime.
That's the assumption, right. So now let's see what the גמרא's Gemara
answer is. OK, the obvi any what obvious difference is is that
it'll obviously be daybreak the next morning, whether the person will actually
get better is not exactly.
You have too much אמונה. emuna.
All right, there you go. Sorry. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי ירמיה שאני טומאה, Amar
Rabbi Yirmiya shani tumah, טומאה tumah is different. Not that night and
day is different than a than having a bad leg. No, here's
what's different. טומאה tumah is different, טומאה tumah doesn't completely sort of
completely remove you from the category. דאית ליה תשלומין בפסח שני. De'it
leh tashlumin bePesach Sheni. Because we know that if somebody is טמא
tamei on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they can פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
So we know an idea of טומאה tuma does not completely exclude
somebody. Okay, so again, that's a little bit bizarre, but here's the
idea about the guy at night who's waiting to bring his קרבן
korban the next day, the issue isn't so much whether he's excluded
or not, the question is whether he's considered to have moved into
the next status. But okay. But if it's just a טומאה tuma
issue, we're more willing to consider the person already in the next,
like, in the category. It's a very funny גמרא. Gemara. I can't
make it better than it is. So, or maybe I could, but
I don't know. Okay, מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif lah Rav Pappa,
רב פפא Rav Pappa asks, הניחא למאן דאמר פסח שני תשלומין דראשון
הוא. Hani nicha l'man d'amar Pesach Sheni tashlumin d'rishon hu. That's fine
if you say פסח שני Pesach Sheni is a makeup for פסח
ראשון, Pesach Rishon, which is of course what we assume. So therefore
being טמא tamei shows that you're not completely excluded. אלא למאן דאמר
שני רגל בפני עצמו הוא, Ela l'man d'amar sheni regel bifnei atzmo
hu, according to the one that says no, this person is exempt
on יום טוב ראשון, Yom Tov Rishon, on the first פסח, Pesach,
and now he has an obligation on פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but
conceptually it's not a makeup of פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. That's a
fascinating debate which we discussed a while ago when we were in
פסחים. Pesachim. So מאי למימרא? mai l'meimra? What can you say? You
can't say that טומאה tuma somehow makes you fundamentally still more in
the category because you don't see that from פסח. Pesach. אלא אמר
רב פפא, Ela amar Rav Pappa, קסבר רבי יוחנן לילה אינו מחוסר
זמן. kasavar Rabbi Yochanan laila eino mechussar zman. All right, that's a
much simpler answer. No, it's an issue of nighttime. Nighttime is not
like you're not yet at the right time of bringing a קרבן.
korban. Since you'll be in the right time the next morning, it's
the right day, sort of הלכה halacha day, it's day eight, it's
just not daytime yet, so you're considered already in the next פרשה
parsha as we would say, in the next category, even though you
have to wait for night to pass because only in the morning
will you be able to bring. But that's enough to consider yourself
already in the next category, which is clearly what's going on there.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says once you're out of day seven, even
though he can't yet bring the קרבן, korban, for that he needs
daybreak, he's considered now in the next phase and therefore he can
become obligated in a second קרבן korban and it won't be a
continuation of the first. This has nothing to do with the idea
that a twisted ankle or something like that would make somebody in
a category of not being obligated and would be a good test
case of this idea of תשלומין דראשון tashlumin d'rishon or תשלומין זה
לזה. tashlumin zeh la'zeh.
Yes, just as a grammar, so לילה אינו מחוסר זמן laila eino
mechussar zman means the fact that it's night does not detract from
his being in the category of that time period which is going
to be defined by the next day.
Right. I mean often מחוסר זמן mechussar zman is used in reference
to the animal, an animal that can't be brought until the next
day, it's not considered to be that it's not yet the זמן
zman of that animal for the קרבן, korban, but here it's being
used also in terms of the person. The fact that it's night
does not mean that it's not yet his time for the קרבן.
korban. It's already the time for the קרבן korban and therefore he's
already moved into a separate category. Yes.
But in the question though, what are you saying is not מחוסר
זמן? mechussar zman? What is the meaning of מחוסר זמן mechussar zman
if it's not מחוסר זמן? mechussar zman?
Well, that's what it means, it just means
the night before, הלכה halacha meaning is how do we look at
this issue? Look, this is the way by the way, if I
were to ask you to describe the מחלוקת machlokes of יוחנן וחזקיה,
Yochanan veChizkiyah, this is exactly what you would say. The person finishes
seven days of טהרה tahara process. He's now completely טהור. tahor. He
now, if you want to sort of בגברא bigavra is fit to
bring a קרבן, korban, right? The only thing is, and it's actually
the right day to bring a קרבן, korban, it's just that it's
nighttime. Does that keep him in the old category or is he
already considered in the new category? So that's the way the גמרא
Gemara is framing it, how do we look at this status of
being the night before. Yes.
What does the term
מחוסר זמן mechussar zman or אינו מחוסר זמן
eino mechussar zman mean in general?
Well, so מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman, you know, again can have a
specific meaning in terms of the fitness of the קרבן. korban. So
like if you, you know, like one example would be for example,
I don't know, like if you שחט shecht an animal, right, ביום
השמיני והלאה ירצה
לקרבן אשה לה'. bayom hashmini vehal'ah yeiratzeh l'korban isheh l'Hashem. So what
happens if it's the night before? I mean,
you know, is that considered to be, you know, yet that the
animal is ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra'uy l'petach ohel mo'ed or not?
So I mean, so it has to be, so the point is
is that often it's in terms of the קרבן, korban, is it
yet the קרבן's korban time, is the קרבן korban of an age
enough, you know, that the קרבן korban can be brought or not
brought, but often it's also applied in this type of a context
about whether the person yet is in the time that's considered to
be, is he in the time period that he's obligated now to
bring the קרבן korban or no, he doesn't become obligated till the
next morning.
Well, just to say לילה אינו מחוסר
זמן
laila eino mechussar
zman
means that just because it's the night before does not mean yet
that it's not his time to bring the קרבן. korban. He's already
obligated.
Right. מחוסר זמן mechussar zman would be it's outside.
It's outside, he's right, it's lacking in the right time to bring
the קרבן. korban. Correct.
Why would you think that you'd measure it from nightfall of the
הלכה halacha day as opposed to what is it, sunrise of the
day? Right.
So this is exactly, look, in general the answer should be easy
because הלכה halacha days count, begin the night before. The interesting thing
to note by קרבנות, korbanot, which has already been noted by the
נציב Netziv and others. is that קרבנות Korbanot days might be counted
by the morning because the general time of bringing a קרבן korban
is the day and the following night. It does not normally follow
the general rule that we have that the night precedes the day,
although I don't see that the גמרא Gemara ever uses that to
reframe conceptually the question of like what is a day, but you
know, but that's certainly you know, could be a strong critique of
this idea of לילה לאו מחוסר זמן. Laila Lav Mechusar Zman. But
in terms of a general orientation, you know, you would say it's
like let's say for example, let's assume it wasn't night and day.
Let's say it was a הלכה halacha you couldn't bring the קרבן
korban until noon. What would be the status, you know, at 11
o'clock, right? So okay, I got to bring it later in the
day, it doesn't mean that now is not yet the day that
I'm obligated. So you know, so if you are committed to this
idea of the night preceding the day, that's partly what the sort
of you know what this is about. Look, maybe the opinion that
it is מחוסר זמן Mechusar Zman fundamentally feels we have to reorient
ourselves in terms of קרבנות Korbanot and not think of night as
connected to the following day. You know, the other point to be
made though here is also that the person stops being טמא tamei
by nightfall. So although they can't bring a קרבן korban until the
day, right, their previous טומאה tumah ended right by nightfall so they
are in this sort of gray zone. This is also a famous
debate of בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai about a
woman who had multiple miscarriages and the obligation to bring another קרבן,
korban, right? So a woman day forty after let's say you know
a miscarriage or after a birth, but even after a miscarriage, would
bring a קרבן korban on her childbirth. So the question is, well,
forty days she's going to bring a קרבן korban the next morning,
let's say she or eighty days because I want to give a
scenario where she became pregnant again, could have a viable child or
whatever. So if it was a girl, eighty days, she's going to
bring has to bring קרבן korban the next morning for her first
birth and let's say she miscarries the night before, right? So is
that again, very parallel debate, is that a continuation and it's all
one קרבן korban because it's seen as like one whole period or
is that separate? So this type of a debate, what happens the
night before somebody is obligated in a קרבן, korban, have they already
entered into that new category or not is like appears multiple times.
But yeah, to some degree it could be a question of how
do you restructure your thinking of days in the world of קרבנות.
Korbanot. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So
okay, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Umi Amar Rabbi Yochanan Hachi? So
now we're going to digress about the issue about whether לילה Laila
is מחוסר זמן. Mechusar Zman. Does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really hold
that לילה Laila is not מחוסר זמן, Mechusar Zman, which certainly seems
to be his point that the טומאה tumah is a continuation? והאמר
רבי יוחנן Veha'amar Rabbi Yochanan ראה אחת בלילה ושתים ביום ra'ah achat
balaila ushtayim bayom
מביא. mevi. שתים בלילה ואחת ביום Shtayim balaila ve'achat bayom אינו מביא.
eino mevi. So this is what I was jumping ahead to before.
Okay, so this is a case here about now a זב. Zav.
א זב A Zav brings, א זב a Zav
is considered, somebody is considered a זב, Zav, a man with a
flow, with a penile flow, that has a certain type of an
appearance, is a זב Zav if he sees and he becomes obligated
in a קרבן korban if this occurs three times over three days
or less. So, so somebody was a זב Zav and then they
were the whole period of טהרה tahara process again, and then the
whole טהרה tahara process was over, they were sort of ready to
bring their קרבן korban and guess what happened? There was, right, the
the night of let me just check רש"י Rashi one more second
just to be precise, hold on.
Right, okay, and then the night
of the seventh
night, he saw a first flow. And then the following morning saw
two more flows. So was that a continuation or is that something
new? Now, if he saw all three flows let's say the next
morning, so then again, it would be obvious. By daybreak he was
obligated in the first קרבן korban and then three flows he became
a זב Zav again and he's obligated in a second קרבן. korban.
Okay, what happens though if it's if it wasn't all the next
day? Some began the night before. And the difference here between whether
you saw one the night before or two the night before, whatever,
is also based on the גמרא Gemara is going to spell this
out but I might as well just tell you that the first
flow of a זב Zav does not categorize him as a זב.
Zav. It actually categorizes him as a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, it's
not treated any different than a seminal flow, even though we're not
talking about semen. He only gets his הלכתי halakhic status as a
זב Zav after two flows. So the assumption is that if one
of the flows was at night, that's why, okay, that's not going
to sort of put him in the previous category. We're really only
going to look at the number of flows that occurs in the
daytime. Okay, so and therefore if two of the flows occurred in
the day, then the day already he's clearly in a separate category.
But if two of the flows occurred at night, so one of
the things that would create his identity as a זב Zav occurred
in the night, then it's a continuation of the previous status. That
would be the idea that in the night he's still considered not
yet in the קרבן korban
obligated קרבן korban status that he would be the next day. So
let's take a look. ראה אחת בלילה ושתים ביום, ra'ah achat balaila
ushtayim bayom, if he had one flow after the seventh day, one
flow at the night of seventh at night and two the next
day, מביא, mevi, he'd go bring another קרבן korban because his new
status of a זב Zav a second time only occurred in the
daytime after he had already been obligated in a קרבן korban at
daybreak. But שתים בלילה *Shtaim b'laila* is two of the flows at
night ואחת ביום *V'achas b'yom* and the third one in the day,
אינו מביא *Eino meivi*, because his new status of a זב zav
*Zav* kicked in already at night before he became obligated in a
קרבן korban, *Korban* in the daytime. So you see that at night
he's not yet considered obligated in a קרבן korban. *Korban*, right, even
though he'll be bringing the next day, he has not yet moved
into his new status.
He's מחוסר זמן *Mechusar zman*, right.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כסבר רב יוחנן *Kasavar Rav Yochanan*,
so that's
a good question. How could רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* here
say the night continues the status, whereas when it came to the
issue before about the what do you call it, what was the
case before, about the נזיר *Nazir* that the night was already the
new status? So how did that work? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אי סלקא דעתך כסבר רב יוחנן לילה layla לאו מחוסר זמן
*Ei salka dach'tach kasavar Rav Yochanan laila lav mechusar zman*, if by
the case of the נזיר *Nazir* רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* held that
the night was already the new status, wasn't yet lacking to be
the new time yet, was already in the new status, so אפילו
שתים בלילה ואחת ביום מביא *Afilu shtaim b'laila v'achas b'yom meivi*. So
therefore even if he had two flows at night, this case
of the what do you call it, of the זב *Zav*, right,
night should already be in his new status and that should be
a new קרבן *Korban*.
No, that's a really good question because it seems ממש *Mamash* the
exact same parallel issue and the exact same conceptual question of when
you're in the night and you're going to bring a קרבן *Korban*
the next day, are you in the new status or not? So
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* sort of concedes. It says כי קאמר רב
יוחנן לדיברי האומר לילה מחוסר זמן *Ki ka'amar Rav Yochanan l'divrei ha'omer
laila mechusar zman*. So רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* is saying personally I
hold that if the guy has a flow, even all three flows
at night, he's already in a new status and he would bring
the new קרבן *Korban*. But according to the person that holds that
the night is not yet a new status, I'm going to tell
you the difference between seeing once at night or seeing twice at
night. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what, he's not talking about
his own opinion? Then why is he bother saying it? לדיברי האומר
*L'divrei ha'omer*, if you're telling me what the position would be from
the person who would say that night would be considered like the
old status and not the new status, so פשיטא *Pshita*, obviously, if
the night I don't need to hear you say that like I
mean if you want to tell me your הלכה halakha *Halacha* position
is that night is still the old status, I understand why you're
telling me this thing of
זב *Zav*. But why do I need you to tell me what
somebody who holds that it's the old status would say? But the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, but here's the חידוש chiddush, *Chidush*. שתים
ביום shtayim ba'yom? ואחת בלילה איצטריכא ליה *Shtaim b'yom v'achas b'laila itztricha
lei*. No, no, no, there is a חידוש *Chidush* here in addition
to just the idea
of whether night is the old status or the new status. The
חידוש *Chidush* is that even if night is the old status, seeing
once would not make a difference. שתים ביום ואחת בלילה איצטריכא ליה
*Shtaim b'yom v'achas b'laila itztricha lei*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *Salka dach'tach amina*,
I would have thought כאתקפתא דרב ששת בריה דרב אידי *K'atakpata d'Rav
Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi*, because this comes up in another גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara*, רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* the son of רב אידי *Rav Idi*
challenges this and he says even one seeing at night should already
put you connect you to the old status because the process began
at night. So even one seeing of night should put you in
the old status. קא משמע לן כדרב יוסף *Ka mashma lan k'd'Rav
Yosef*. No, the response that רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* says back is
what I told you that the first seeing doesn't yet classify the
person as a זב *Zav*. The first seeing the person is just
in the status of a בעל קרי *Ba'al keri*, so the first
seeing is immaterial. So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said is that
רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* actually holds that night is the new status.
So if a person becomes a what do you call it, a
נזיר *Nazir*, so the case of a נזיר *Nazir* becomes טמא *Tamei*
again at night, it's already a new קרבן *Korban*. If the person
was a זב *Zav* and started seeing at night, one, two, three
flows, it would already be a new קרבן *Korban*. The night is
already the new status. This teaching was according to the one that
says the night is the old status. So then you might think
that even one flow already creates a sense of continuity and it's
not a new קרבן *Korban*. And the חידוש *Chidush* is no, one
flow is not yet significant. It's only two flows at night would
create that sense of continuity and say that it would still be
one קרבן *Korban* not two קרבנות *Korbanot*. So we have went far
afield from our discussion about the nature of חגיגה *Chagigah* and whether
it's תשלומין tashlumin, דראשון *Tashlumin d'rishon* or not תשלומין tashlumin. דראשון *Tashlumin
d'rishon* and really this whole discussion is pretty irrelevant because you know
I mean okay that's a fascinating conversation but that's an issue of
when have you moved into a new status if you're going to
bring a קרבן *Korban* the next day but you can't bring it
at night but הלכתית *Halachically* it's the next day and your טהרה
*Tahara* process finished the day before. Okay so that's a debate that
we get in all of ש"ס *Shas* about לילה מחוסר זמן *Laila
mechusar zman*. But again it has not really given us any sharper
understanding of this debate of whether the fundamental obligation is day one
and the rest of the days are makeup or whether fundamentally it's
really an obligation bring it any day and you're יוצא *Yotzei*, maybe
a preference for day one but bring it any day and you're
יוצא *Yotzei*. That still remains a sort of unclarified debate. But to
me the fascinating part about it is number one is the assumption
that the identity between the מצוה mitzvah, *Mitzvah* of עולת ראיה *Olat
re'iyah* and the שלמי חגיגה *Shalmei chagigah*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just
in passing assumes that the person
exempt from
עולת ראיה *Olat re'iyah* is exempt
from שלמי חגיגה *Shalmei chagigah*, and also the question also... that the
גמרא Gemara has said here about whether to see the other days
as a makeup or to see them as equivalent. Do you have
a question? Yeah.
אחד בלילה שתים ביום. achad ba'laila, shtayim ba'yom.
Why would you need שתים ביום? The one at לילה is immaterial.
Because you don't bring... no, it's not immaterial. A person needs to
have to see three times in order to be a זב who
is obligated in a קרבן, but the first time is not yet
considered the beginning of the process of זיבה. ziva. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: Alright, now
we get to a little אגדתא.
aggadata. One sort of הלכה halakha issue in the משנה Mishnah did
not really get further clarified not even in the משנה, Mishnah, it
was the אמורא Amoraic discussion
related to the issue of the משנה Mishnah of the idea of
תשלומין, tashlumin, that did not get further clarified. And now we get
to the interesting little אגדתא aggadata discussion going on in the משנה
Mishnah about somebody who missed he had a makeup time, you had
seven days to make it up. You didn't make it up? Alright,
now you've blown it. מעוות לא יוכל לתקן וחסרון לא יוכל להמנות.
me'uvat lo yuchal litkon vechesaron lo yuchal lhimanot.
Just to remind you what happened in the משנה, Mishnah, the סתם
stam משנה Mishnah made that statement about the person who blew his
opportunity to bring the קרבן חגיגה. korban chagiga. רב שמעון בן מנסיא
Reb Shimon ben Menasya said no,
that's actually where there's... it's not just like you didn't do a
מצוה, mitzvah, but there's actually some lasting injury created as a result.
It's מעוות, me'uvat, right? It's one thing like a
חסרון, chesaron, okay, you didn't do the thing you were supposed to
do, you know, it was a lacking. But מעוות me'uvat is a
perversion. So he speaks about the idea of an act of adultery
or incest which produces a ממזר, mamzer, which really creates something like
a... it really has this negative, you know, real-world negative impact about
the person's עבירה, aveira, a lasting impact that cannot be fixed. And
then you had רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabi Shimon ben Yochai says
that it has to do something that began okay and then was
perverted, not just the creation of something bad, but the perversion of
something that started good, and he speaks about תלמיד חכם הפורש מן
התורה. talmid chacham haparesh min hatorah. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara, sort of says about this. אמר רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Amar
Rabi Shimon ben Yochai, al ze ne'emar מעוות לא יוכל לתקן וחסרון
לא יוכל להמנות. me'uvat lo yuchal litkon vechesaron lo yuchal lhimanot. אמר
לי בר הי הי להלל. Amar lei Bar Hei Hei l'Hillel. So
he has בר הי, Bar Hei, which we almost never hear. We
have בן בג בג Ben Bag-Bag and בר הי הי. Bar Hei
Hei. So by the way, just to show you this cute little
תוספות, Tosafot, בר הי הי Bar Hei Hei says יש מפרשים שגר
היה והיינו בן אברהם ושרה שנתווסף ה בשמן. yesh mefarshim sheger haya
vehayno ben Avraham v'Sarah she-nitosef hei bishman. Right, אברהם Avraham got the
extra ה hei and שרה Sarah got the extra ה. hei. So
he's בר הי הי. Bar Hei Hei. וכן בג בג דכולה דגמרא
עולה לה או כולה דבג, vechein Bag-Bag d'chula d'Gemara oleh l'hei or
chula d'Bag, whatever. Anyway, the בג, Bag, ב bet and ג, gimel,
equals five. So it's pretty fun, like בר הי הי, Bar Hei
Hei, בן בג בג, Ben Bag-Bag, some of the funniest names in
the גמרא. Gemara תוספות Tosafot points out it's the same גימטריה gematria
as five and maybe there's some significance there. Okay, so anyway, let's
take a look. אמר לי בר הי הי להלל, Amar lei Bar
Hei Hei l'Hillel, האי להמנות? למלאות מיבעי ליה hai l'himanot? l'himalot miba'ei
lei? Like when it
says something lacking that cannot be counted, according to you, you know,
you didn't do a מצוה, mitzvah it's like a something lacking that
can't be filled, like you know, like the hole can't be filled,
there was something missing. What do you mean counted? Where's the idea
of counting come in here?
אלא זה שנמנו חבריו לדבר מצוה והוא לא נמנה עמהם. Ella ze
shenimnu chaverav l'dvar mitzvah vehu lo nimna imahem. There was a group
getting together to do a מצוה mitzvah and there was a counting
that was taking place and you weren't counted among them. So it's
not just a מצוה mitzvah, that wasn't done, but it's actually to
stand up and be counted. There was an opportunity to stand up
and be counted and you weren't there. תניא נמי הכי: Tanya nami
hachi: מעוות לא יוכל לתקן, me'uvat lo yuchal litkon, זה שביטל קריאת
שמע של שחרית או קריאת שמע של ערבית. ze shebittel kriat shema
shel shacharit o kriat shema shel arvit. So that's something that cannot
be fixed, as opposed to that cannot be filled, cannot be counted,
cannot be fixed, like you missed קריאת שמע kriat shema so you
blew it. או שביטל תפילה של שחרית או תפילה של ערבית, O
shebittel tefillah shel shacharit o tefillah shel arvit, or a person missed
davening of שחרית shacharit or davening of ערבית. arvit. Now that is
quite fascinating, right? Because that could be made up. As תוספות Tosafot
points out, there's תשלומין. tashlumin So no, so תוספות Tosafot points out
that that's actually part of the חידוש, that even though there's a
sense of תשלומין, תשלומין doesn't totally fix it, which is an interesting
idea. Right? But why of all things? And there's a million מצוות
mitzvot you could say somebody didn't do. Right? So it's very fascinating
why these are chosen, and particularly the תפילה tefillah which actually does
have some aspect of a makeup, although תוספות Tosafot says maybe that's
דוקא davka the point. וחסרון לא יוכל להמנות זה שנמנו חבריו לדבר
מצוה והוא לא נמנה עמהם. Vechesaron lo yuchal lhimanot, ze shenimnu chaverav
l'dvar mitzvah vehu lo nimna imahem.
People were standing up to be counted to do a מצוה, to
be participating, to be part of the group, and you blew your
opportunity, you were not among them. So by the way, the other
nice thing about that point is that it's not just like shirking
an obligation, which is like more obvious, it's even not having that
initiative or not stepping forward to seize an opportunity. Right? So even
that there's, you know, a person can be held accountable. אמר לי
בר הי הי
להלל. Amar lei Bar
Hei Hei l'Hillel. So now בר הי Bar Hei says to הלל,
Hillel, since we're talking about בר הי Bar Hei and הלל: Hillel:
מאי דכתיב ושבתם וראיתם בין צדיק לרשע בין עובד אלהים לאשר לא
עבדו? mai d'chtiv v'shavtem u're-item bein tzaddik l'rasha bein oved elohim la-asher
lo avado? You'll go back and see between the righteous and the
wicked, between one who serves God and one who does not serve
God. היינו צדיק היינו עובד אלהים היינו רשע היינו אשר לא עבדו.
Hainu tzaddik hainu oved elohim, hainu rasha hainu asher lo avado. That's
a redundant verse. So the righteous is somebody who serves God, alright.
The wicked is somebody who doesn't serve God. What's the verse adding?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so Hillel said to him, so עבדו ולא
עבדו תרווייהו צדיקי גמורי נינהו. avado v'lo avado tarvaihu tzaddikei gemurei ninhu.
No,
serving God, not serving God, you could be righteous. Now, again, you
know, we would say a צדיק, tzaddik, but somebody who fully does
all their obligations but doesn't, you know, go that extra mile, doesn't
really strive to serve God beyond just satisfying their basic obligations. So
what would be the example? צדיקי
גמורי נינהו, Tzaddikei gemurei ninhu, I like the idea, complete צדיקים. tzaddikim.
He calls somebody who is לא עבדו lo avado צדיקי גמורי נינהו.
tzaddikei gemurei ninhu. ואינו דומה, Ve'eino domeh, but here's the difference. שונה
פרקו מאה פעמים, Shoneh pirko me'ah pe'amim, somebody that learns his chapter,
meaning חזר chazar his learning a hundred times, לשונה פרקו מאה ואחת,
leshoneh pirko me'ah va'achas,
to somebody who learns it a hundred and one. Go, you know,
it's like we say I want you to give 110%. 100%, yes,
it's a
צדיק גמור, tzaddik gamur, but that's not a real עובד אלהים. oved
Elokim. לא עובד Lo oved is a guy who just doesn't do
his obligations. But עובד אלהים oved Elokim is the guy who gives
it 110% or 101 times. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said back to him, so ומשום חד זימנא קרי ליה לא עבדו?
umishum chad zimna karei lei lo avado?
Because he did once time less, it's somebody who did not serve
God? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אין, ein, yes. צא ולמד משוק של
חמורין, Tze u'lamad mishuk shel chamorin,
go look at the marketplace of the donkey, you know, the donkey
drivers, the people who rent out their donkeys. עשרה פרסי פרסי בזוזא,
Asarah parsei parsi bezuza,
they charge you one zuz to take the donkey go ten פרסי.
parsei. Okay? חד עשר פרסי, Chad asar parsei,
one more step beyond the ten פרסי, parsei, you know, eleven פרסי,
parsei, בתרי זוזי, bitrei zuzei, the cost will be double. Right? You're
already into the next day, right? Rental car.
You're even in the next borough, like Jacob the Rapper. Oh right.
No, the best example is like a car rental, right? They don't
prorate, do they prorate it when you go into the next day
or they charge you a full another day? Sometimes. Sometimes. Depends I
guess on the car rental company, right? But you go one thing
over and already it's a whole, it's a whole...
The better example is the car service. They charge you double the
second you cross into Westchester. Oh, that's good, like Michael was saying.
Okay, anyway, anyway, the point is is that there's a normal limit
to things, right? People are normally expected and you go up to
the maximum, but you know, just one thing to go up to
the maximum, there's a clear sense of going beyond the normal limit.
And that extra going beyond transforms conceptually, qualitatively, sort of the, you
know, sort of the meaning of the act and the status of
the person, the person who's willing to go that one extra thing.
Now, by the way, that implies that a hundred times to do
חזרה chazarah is seen as a standard. Right? It's not like everybody
does חזרה chazarah five times, you did it a hundred and you
did it a hundred and one, right? So you could do 97,
you could do 98. It feels like there's that sense like, anyway,
oh, the real way to learn, do חזרה, chazarah, you do it
a hundred times. And this guy decided he's going to do it
one extra. Now that to us sounds very hard to imagine, but
again, I don't know if there's been any studies of this, but
in an oral culture, you gotta repeat things a lot, right? We're
not necessarily saying that you're doing all of your גמרא Gemara. a
hundred times, but if you're learning all the material and you're memorizing
all the material, maybe there really was a practice of you do
a standard way you memorize it is you repeat it a hundred
times, and this guy's saying I'm going to actually push myself and
do even more than is the norm. Now the מהרש"א Maharsha points
out a great little גימטריה gematria that עובד אלהים לאשר, oved Elokim
la'asher, right? So עין, ayin, if you take the ראשי תיבות, rashei
teivos, עין ayin עובד oved אלהים Elokim אלף aleph and לאשר la'asher
למד lamed is 101. And לא עבדו, lo avado, the ראשי תיבות
rashei teivos למד lamed and the עין ayin is 100. So that
might be where the גמרא Gemara is getting the 101 versus the
100. Yeah.
Also, is with פרקו, pirko, like his פרק, perek, maybe reference like
in an oral culture like, hey, you're the guy that memorized this
פרק... perek...
Oh,
that's an interesting idea. Yeah, so did they ever really do that?
There was a, you know, there was like a myth, I mean
scholars say that this isn't true, but there was a myth that
like, you know, when they were trying to figure out like how
did all of the בעלי תוספות Ba'alei Tosafot like be able to
like know stuff from like, you know, all of, you know, all
of, how'd they have all it at their fingertips, right? You know,
so there was like this myth that like it's like, it's like
in the בעלי תוספות's Ba'alei Tosafot's בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, like you
would had, you'd be the סוכה Sukkah guy, you'd be the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah guy, you'd be the זבחים Zevachim guy, and I'd
be learning a סוגיא, sugya, and then I'd go around the בית
מדרש Beis Medrash and say does anybody know any relevant סוגיא sugya
from זבחים, Zevachim, from סוכה, Sukkah, from whatever, and then that's how
they would have random access. But that they say isn't true. But
in terms of your idea, like in the time of the גמרא,
Gemara גמרא Gemara teaches from, about רב חסדא Rav Chisda that he
says like, is that what you were going to say? Yeah, how
I would sort of prevent תורה Torah from being lost that I'd
go around and disseminate, you know, דברי תורה, divrei Torah, and I,
you know, each person would have to learn a different section and
teach it to everybody else. So that's interesting. So maybe it is
a sense of not just, you know, normal things people are learning,
but that they're learning with the responsibility to teach and be responsible
for. Yeah, is that what you were going to say though? Yes,
yeah, okay.
So, yeah, and this is a language in that סוגיא sugya in
עירובין Eiruvin about, about going into the אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed and
learning and being taught by משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, פרקו. pirko. Was
it פרקו? pirko?
Oh, so that was,
oh that's a good point. So that reinforces
Ben's point, and that maybe that sort of brings the poignancy of
this issue that he's a responsibility... he has a responsibility to teach
it, while everybody heard everybody else's, terrific, four times.
And on
a slightly lighter note relevant to this, about 101, יפה, Yafeh, you
know that scene from Spinal Tap where he says it goes to
11? It goes to 11.
I don't understand, but this goes to 11. Anyway,
alright, so the גמרא Gemara says,
alright, this is probably the only דף יומי Daf Yomi you're going
to have somebody quote Spinal Tap, but I'll tell you that. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Alright, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this: אמר ליה אליהו לבר
הי הי. Amar lei Eliyahu le-Bar Hei Hei. Since we're talking about
בר הי הי, Bar Hei Hei, now we have אליהו Eliyahu having
an encounter with בר הי הי. Bar Hei Hei. ואמרי ליה לרבי
אלעזר, Ve-amrei lei le-Rabbi Elazar, some say it was רבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Elazar. מאי דכתיב? Mai d'ichtiv? So אליהו Eliyahu said to him, what's
meant by the verse: הנה צרפתיך ולא בכסף? Hinei tzerafticha ve-lo ve-chesef?
Behold, I have smelted you, but not with now, literally it means
with silver, although רש"י Rashi says it means not as silver, like
not as silver would be smelted. בחרתיך, Becharticha, I've tested you like
tested your quality, בכור עוני, Be-chor oni, in the furnace of poverty.
What? בכור, Be-chor, do you mean, right?
כור? Kur? No,
בכור.
Be-chor. I think it's but it's whatever, it's בכור, be-chor, but it's
not a בכור. bechor. Anyway, in the furnace of poverty. מלמד שחזר
הקדוש ברוך הוא על כל מדות טובות ליתן לישראל. Melamed she-chazar ha-Kadosh
Baruch Hu al kol middot tovot liten le-Yisrael. God was looking around
for all good qualities to give to the Jewish people. This is
apparently what he said back to אליהו. Eliyahu. ולא מצא אלא עניות,
Ve-lo matza ela aniyut,
and the best quality he could find to give them was poverty.
אמר שמואל ואיתימא רב יוסף, Amar Shmuel ve-itima Rav Yosef, היינו דאמרי
אינשי, Hainu d'amri inshi,
that's what people say: יאה עניותא ליהודאי, Ya'ah aniyuta le-Yhuda'ei,
poverty is good for the Jewish people, כי ברזא סומקא לסוסיא חיורא,
ki barza sumka le-susya chivra,
like a red strap for a white horse. That somehow, I don't
know, keeps him in line, it keeps him frum. You know, this
is interesting, it goes back to the earlier גמרא, Gemara right? That
first dealt with all of the tragedy of the חורבן הבית Churban
HaBayit and then tried to reframe it in a positive way. So
here it is sort of talking about, you know, maybe if you
have too much wealth, you go off the דרך, derech, you keep
poor, it keeps you on the right path. And as the מהרש"א
Maharsha actually says, that the point of the ולא בכסף ve-lo ve-chesef
might be that point, meaning not that not as silver would be
smelted, but I smelted you by not having silver, like the form,
the way you were smelted was the sort of that parallels the
word of עני oni later. You know, like with the absence of
silver, that was how you have been tested, your quality, your steel
has been tested in that way. Okay, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר:
Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer: איזהו מעוות לא יוכל לתקן זה הבא
על הערוה והוליד ממנה ממזר. Eizehu me'uvat lo yuchal litkon zeh ha-ba
al ha-ervah ve-holid mimena mamzer. So now we move on to the
idea of lasting damage of the sin, yes.
But maybe the חזר הקדוש ברוך הוא chazar ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu point
isn't God went over all of them and the best one he
found was this. It's the claim is he went over all of
them and the only one he gave to Israel was poverty.
When it says ולא מצא אלא עני- ve-lo matza ela ani- oh.
He went over all of them and he's like,
oh, he passed all of them. Yeah, but I don't know if
ולא מצא ve-lo matza would have worked then. He couldn't find one.
Anyway, alright, but it is obviously clearly, look,
right? Look, it's true that Jews have stayed frummer when they've been
oppressed and had I mean, not when they've been killed, and they,
but you know, when they've had it bad than when they've had
it good. You know, that leads people, tends to lead people astray.
Whether that's something to want is a different
question, right? You can't sin, you can't do מצוות mitzvot either. You
can't have more Jews either.
That's also what went to Rebbe. What? Exactly.
Alright, moving on. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay,
איזהו מעוות לא יוכל לתקן זה הבא על הערוה והוליד ממנה ממזר.
Eizehu me'uvat lo yuchal litkon zeh ha-ba al ha-ervah ve-holid mimena mamzer.
Now, I want to just make a point before we continue reading,
that of course the simple sense of this is that there's lasting
damage that a person has created, right? And that's compared to the
idea if you steal from somebody, you can correct the damage that
you've created. Here there's damage that's been created that can't be corrected,
and it's about sort of an injury done to others or an
injury done to the world. But it is worth noting a troubling
רש"י, Rashi, I would say, on the משנה, Mishna, because רש"י Rashi
says on explaining this, והוליד ממזר, ve-holid mamzer, on דף ט עמוד
א, Daf Tet Amud Aleph, like the first narrow line: שהביא פסולים
בישראל והיא זכרון לחטאו לפיכך אין עונותיו נמחקים בתשובה. She-hevi psulim be-Yisrael
ve-hi zikaron le-chato le-fichach ein avonotav nimchakim bi-tshuva. So
like the problem is not so much the way the world has
been hurt as a result of this person's sins, but since the
product of the sin is still around, then the person can't be
forgiven. Like, so it's more concern about the person being able to
be forgiven for his sins than to be able to correct the
injury and the damage created by his sins. To me, it's a
little you understand the difference of focusing on our concern for the
person rather than our concern for the impact that the person had.
Anyway, that's what רש"י Rashi says. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara הוליד אין לא הוליד
לא? Holid in, lo holid lo? One minute. So there's only a
problem, an unfixable problem, after a child has been born? והתניא, Ve-hatanya,
we taught in a ברייתא: Braita: רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר... Rabbi
Shimon ben Menasya omer... רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya omer גונב אדם אפשר שיחזיר גנבתו goneiv adam efshar sheyachazir gneivato
if a person steals, robs, like burglars you can return it. ויתקן
veyitaken and fix it. גוזל אדם gozeil adam person if a person
robs or steals, excuse me, אפשר שיחזיר גזלתו efshar sheyachazir gezeilato he
can return what he stole. ויתקן veyitaken and fix it. אבל הבא
על אשת איש aval haba al eishet ish but but if a
man had sex with a married woman ואסרה לבעלה ve'asra l'ba'alah and
made her forbidden to her husband, ניטרד מן העולם והלך לו, nitrad
min ha'olam v'halach lo, he'll be wasted from the world and the,
you know, he'll go into, you know, he'll go to destruction
because he's created a lasting injury. So this also probably is where
רש״י's Rashi picking up on that, because here's a concern is ניטרד
מן העולם. nitrad min ha'olam. Right? Look at what's going... this person
will never be forgiven because his sin has this lasting impact. So
the focus here is on the sin, you know what the person,
you know what the person has done. Meaning not what the person
has done but sort of, you know, the person's status is now
irreparable, not just that the effect of what he has done is
irreparable. Anyway, but what we see from this is is that it's
even without a child there's an irreparable damage that's done because the
woman is now forbidden to her husband. So the גמרא Gemara says,
wait let's see the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer, אין אומרים, ein omrim,
and רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai like in our
משנה Mishna says
no, מעוות me'uvat is only something that started good and became not
good. So אין אומרים ein omrim בקרו גמל bikru gamal בקרו חזיר,
bikru chazir,
you don't say hey let's check out this camel or check out
this pig and see if we can bring it for a קרבן.
Right? Because of course you can't, who cares if it has a
מום mum or not? It's a pig, it's a camel. אלא בקרו
טלה, ela bikru taleh, so check out this sheep and let's see
if it has a מום. mum. So to pervert something is something
that's good and that now has a מום mum and damage and
become not good. ואיזהו, v'eizehu, what would that be? זה תלמיד חכם
שפירש מן התורה. zeh talmid chacham shepirash min hatorah. That's again, like
he said in our משנה, Mishna, a תורה Torah sage that has
left the world of תורה Torah and maybe even left observance or
certainly, and that is something that is מעוות, me'uvat, or maybe just
left תורה Torah but will never recapture what that person has lost,
will never be able to make it up. That is something that
has been perverted. Now I gotta tell you this is disturbing because
here he's responding not to the idea of a ממזר, mamzer, you
could say a ממזר mamzer was always born a ממזר, mamzer, but
here he's referring to the case about the woman being forbidden to
her husband. Well that certainly perverted something that was good, right? There
was a marriage that you've now this person has ruined. So I
really don't understand this response to the example here about the impact
on the marriage. רבי יהודה בן לקיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish anyway
finish this and then see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. רבי
יהודה בן לקיש אומר Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish omer כל תלמיד חכם
שפירש מן התורה kol talmid chacham shepirash min hatorah עליו הכתוב אומר,
alav hakatuv omer, any תורה Torah sage that has left תורה, Torah,
regarding him the verse says כציפור נודדת מן קנה katzipor nodedet min
kanah like a bird that will sort of, did
he say יהודה בן לקיש? Yehuda ben Lakish?
I don't know, could be. Like a bird like a bird that's
sort of you know travels, flutters, or whatever or from its nest,
כן איש נודד ממקומו, ken ish noded mimekomo, same person who leaves
his place. ואומר, v'omer, so you're leaving your nest, you're leaving your
home, ואומר מה מצאו אבותיכם בי עול כי רחקו מעלי. v'omer ma
matzu avoteichem bi avel ki rachaku me'alai. What wrong did
you know what perversion did your forefathers see in me that they
have distanced themselves from me? Why would a person who has found
a life of meaning and a life of תורה Torah you know
all of a sudden decide to leave? And now again leaving it
might not mean to stop being observant but might just mean I
don't know to leave it to go into business. But anyway but
this statement here is certainly less critical I would say than the
statement that it's מעוות לא יוכל לתקון. me'uvat lo yuchal litkon. Right?
It's just like, you know, it's just like why would you leave
your home? Why would you leave your nest? What problem did you
find? Number one it's not as saying that this is a perversion
and it's also not saying that it cannot be corrected. So it's
like saying okay it's not good but we're not going to go
that far. But again it's interesting that רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai sort of you know it's one thing to interpret
it that way it's another thing to say it can't mean what
you said. I mean the guy also in the first case the
guy did destroy the marriage. So anyway or the man and the
woman together did but anyway. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this
anyway so how does it answer this problem? Why did we say
that it had to be a ממזר? mamzer? You could do this
lasting perversion even without a ממזר mamzer without having the child. לא
קשיא lo kashya כאן באחותו פנויה kan ba'achoto penuyah כאן באשת איש.
kan b'eishet ish. There are two acts of forbidden sex there's incest
and there's adultery. So in the case of incest you know the
sort of lasting perversion we're not obviously talking about the psychological impact
that's completely being passed over here. So the lasting perversion is if
a child is born and the ממזר mamzer whereas in the case
of adultery there there's a lasting perversion done in terms of the
destruction of the marriage. Charlie you had a question before? We're gonna
have some other... I think he's going to bring up the sister
part. Oh there you go see that. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'it eima now
that's one thing I gotta tell you these next things are deeply
disturbing. ואיבעית אימא v'iba'it eima if you want you could say הא
והא באשת איש ha v'ha b'eishet ish two scenarios of a case
of marriage. And so why would one require a child to be
born for there to be a lasting
perversion? לא קשיא lo kashya כאן באונס kan b'ones כאן ברצון. kan
b'ratzon. Difference between rape and willing. So you imagine what the גמרא
Gemara is saying right? I mean just so so much looking at
it in this very narrow halakhic way. Well if the woman was
raped then she's not going to be forbidden to her husband so
then the lasting damage is only created if a child is born.
But if it's willing then she becomes forbidden. And what about the
lasting damage created by the act of rape? Right? That's completely being
ignored. Like the actual, you know, psychic and physical, but even more
like psychic emotional damage to the woman, that we're not looking at.
We're looking through sort of the halachic ways in which things have
been perverted. So therefore rape in a way is not as bad
as willing and it'll only be an issue if a child is
born. Very difficult גמרא. Gemara Let's just read the other answers. איבעית
אימא הוה באונס, Ibayit eima hava b'ones, or two cases of rape
and what what what's the difference? לא קשיא כאן באשת כהן כאן
באשת ישראל. Lo kashya kan b'eis kohen kan b'eis Yisrael. If if
it's a wife of a כהן, kohen, then even rape she's forbidden
to her husband. If it's a wife of a non-כהן, kohen, then
only if a ממזר, mamzer, then she's not forbidden by rape and
there would only be a lasting problem if a ממזר mamzer was
born. So again, very very, you know, difficult, you know, to read
this and not sort of that the גמרא's Gemara sort of, you
know, sort of not addressing the type of sense of violence that
is done through the act of rape, right? And that that's itself,
you know, why didn't the גמרא Gemara say a lasting perversion if
somebody kills somebody, somebody breaks somebody's arm? You know, that's a good
example, you can pay as much money as you want, you're not
going to correct it. So anyway, so it's again interesting, you know,
and troubling that this is what the גמרא Gemara says. Yes, Ben.
Here's- and that might be why רש״י Rashi focuses on the תשובה.
teshuvah. There's so many obvious examples of sins that cause permanent effect
on the world.
Yeah,
but if those are permanent effects, if somebody's killed somebody, then that
permanent effect is around, same question, how should that person be able
to do תשובה teshuvah if the effect is around? Right? The רש״י's
Rashi still saying
it's the point that there is a permanent effect and therefore therefore,
you know, it's- is the problem we're focusing on the effect or
the impact on the person? But the scenario is a permanent effect.
All good point. I guess kind of like distasteful to interpret it
this way, but one of the things that comes out from that
first, that first answer of, 'Oh, it's talking about one is rape
and one is is willing,' is also, it's also it seems comes
out that it's much easier to do תשובה teshuvah for a rape
than to תשובה teshuvah for a consensual adulterous act. I think that's
like- right, well
again, if you frame this גמרא Gemara. as a question of ease
to do תשובה, teshuvah, which is sort of like רש״י's Rashi way,
right, you don't have to contend with the the impact of your
act in one case, you know, whereas in the other case, you
know, you do. Again, but the problem is that it's ignoring the
impact of an act of rape, right? That's the the problem. But
right, but, you know, but look in a way you could say,
you know,
but yes, I mean that is what it's saying because it's focusing
on the challenge created by this lasting impact and in one case
can be, you know, if that can't be addressed that remains a
permanent obstacle. Yes.
I found specifically the part about the בת כהן bat kohen and
then בת ישראל bat Yisrael forbidden them, like very clearly- that's disturbing
in itself, that's just- but that's like a הלכה halakha that's- punished
for- right.
Look, that's true, I mean that's, you know, right, anything
that's- yeah, so that's like
I'm going to bracket that till we get to
יבמות, Yevamot, which is
the מסכת masechet coming up, so we'll get to it there, but
yeah and you know there's practical ways of dealing with that nowadays
certainly, but you're right, I mean that as a הלכה halakha, is
very, you know, is a is a very deeply disturbing and challenging
הלכה, Halakha. absolutely, yes. So it's one thing to say the גמרא
Gemara doesn't deal with
the psychic damage of the rape but is concerned only with halachic
categories. Another thing to say there are halachic categories that could have
dealt with the psychic damage, but the גמרא Gemara? chose not to
raise them. I assume you mean the latter, not the- yeah, I
mean, you know, there are like, you know, צער tza'ar and בושת
boshet and those types of things.
I mean they're not the same type of, you know,
it's not the same severity we would put on that act today,
but there are definitely some categories to apply. But yeah, again, like
all acts of violence are not being discussed here. Those are if
you want to ask what's a lasting damage somebody can create that
no matter how much תשובה teshuvah you do you cannot fully correct,
the most obvious examples are acts of violence against other people, right?
So alright,
let's finish up the גמרא. Gemara ויוצא ולבא אין שלום, U'yotzei l'bo
ein shalom, the one who leaves and comes there will be no
peace. What does that mean? אמר רב, Amar Rav, כיון שיוצא אדם
מדבר הלכה לדבר מקרא, keivan she'yotzei adam mid'var halakha l'dvar mikra, so
since we talked about leaving תורה Torah and I said doesn't even
mean leaving observance, just leaving the world of תורה Torah to go
into business, now we're going to even up the stakes, even a
certain type of a change of focus in תורה Torah can be
seen as a bad thing. Okay,
so leaving and coming. כיון שיוצא אדם מדבר הלכה לדבר מקרא, keivan
she'yotzei adam mid'var halakha l'dvar mikra, if somebody leaves a like learning
תורה Torah to נעבעך nebach go ahead and learn you know you
know Bible, so then שוב אין לו שלום shuv ein lo shalom
won't have any peace because you know it's not as satisfying of
a learning, it doesn't lead to clarifying observance, you know the גמרא
Gemara tends to disparage the learning of just of just Bible in
itself, of מקרא mikra in itself, like the famous גמרא is, you
know, you know הלומד מקרא מדה ואינה מדה, halomed mikra mida v'eino
mida, you know if somebody learns like Bible it's like it's good
but it's not great, you know if you learn גמרא אין לך
מדה גדולה מזו. ein lecha mida gedola mizo. So here too like
you know so you you know if you go from a serious-
into a not so serious learning, it's not a good thing. And
also אין שלום ein shalom presumably might also mean it doesn't help
you in terms of your observance. And that way אין שלום, ein
shalom, which is what רש״י Rashi says, like four lines down in
the narrow lines, רש״י Rashi says שאין הוראה מדבר מקרא שהמשנה מפרשת
סתימת התורה she'ein hora'ah midvar Mikra she'haMishnah mefareshas stimas haTorah
that you don't get any clear direction like as you do by
learning הלכה. Halakha Let's just read some of the other examples. ושמואל
אמר זה הפורש
מתלמוד
למשנה. VeShmuel amar zeh haporish miTalmud leMishnah. No, even leaving גמרא and
learning משנה. Mishnah. משנה Mishnah also just has a lot of information
but it's not you're not thinking the matters through so it's not
as challenging. You're not unpacking them and analyzing them and comparing them
and thinking them through. It's more just memorizing statements. And also you
don't really know the הלכה based on משנה Mishnah because you haven't
done the necessary analysis. רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אפילו מש״ס לש״ס, afilu mishas leshas, even going
from גמרא to גמרא. So from which גמרא to which גמרא? So
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos discuss going from בבלי Bavli to ירושלמי
Yerushalmi but which one is the good one and which one is
the bad one? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael but he might have meant leaving the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and
going to the בבלי Bavli but רש״י Rashi claims he means leaving
the בבלי Bavli and going to the ירושלמי Yerushalmi because the בבלי
Bavli is more demanding and more challenging and therefore like a more
serious learning. But then, yeah, that's what רש״י Rashi said. Well, if
you know Palestinian Aramaic like your רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan then the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi anyway. But anyway, if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafos, the fourth line here on תוספות Tosafos at the top, he
says ומיהו אפילו איפכא יש לומר. umeehu afilu ipcha yesh lomar. Really
whichever way you go, בבלי Bavli to ירושלמי Yerushalmi or ירושלמי Yerushalmi
to בבלי, Bavli, it would, you might say this statement, והכי פירושו
שפירש מזה ועדיין לא הבין בזה. vehachi perusho shepeirish mizeh ve'adayin lo
heivin bezeh.
You leave one before you've mastered, mastered, right? I'm getting bored with
this, I'll go to another. And you keep on switching topics and
you never give it the focus needed to get the necessary mastery,
שמתוך כך לא יעלה בידו הלכה ברורה. shemitoch kach lo ya'aleh beyado
halakha berurah.
Then you keep on flitting from one to another. Okay, but anyway,
notice here the גמרא just says אין שלום, ein shalom, it doesn't
say מובטח לו שלא יוכל לקום, muvtach lo shelo yuchal lakum, right?
So yes, in a sense, because
you see the context, if you change your field, it doesn't mean
that you're doing something negative necessarily, but you're going to have trouble.
Aha, right, and you're kind of constantly looking around maybe for a
change. Exactly. That's true. Yeah. Although it is interesting that all the
examples in the גמרא go in one way, בבלי Bavli to ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi.
Right, right.
Okay,
I see everybody's getting up.
Has anyone ever studied סדר טהרות? Seder Tahoros? What do you mean?
Because you haven't mastered everything else? All right, good question.
All right, we will
end here.